Getting Started Guide

The getting started is broken up into the following sections:

Getting Started on the ESP32 platform

Getting Started on the STM32 platform

Getting Started on the Generic UNIX platform

Getting Started on the ESP32 platform

The AtomVM virtual machine is supported on the Espressif ESP32 platform, allowing users to write Erlang and Elixir programs and deploy them to the ESP32 micro-controller.

These instructions cover how to get the AtomVM virtual machine flashed to your ESP32 device, as well as how to flash your Erlang and Elixir programs that will be executed by the virtual machine running on the device.

For most applications, you should only need to install the VM once (or at least once per desired AtomVM release). Once the VM is uploaded, you can then begin development of Erlang or Elixir applications, which can then be flashed as part of your routine development cycle.

Requirements

Deployment of AtomVM applications requires the following components:

A computer running MacOS or Linux (Windows support is not currently supported);

An ESP32 module with a USB/UART connector (typically part of an ESP32 development board);

A USB cable capable of connecting the ESP32 module or board to your development machine (laptop or PC);

The esptool program, for flashing the AtomVM image and AtomVM programs;

An Erlang/OTP release (21, 22, or 23);

A serial console program, such as minicom or screen, so that you can view console output from your AtomVM application.

(optional) For Erlang programs, rebar3;

(optional) For Elixir programs, mix, which ships with the Elixir runtime;

Deployment Overview

The ES32 AtomVM virtual machine is an IDF application that runs on the ESP32 platform. As an IDF application, it provides the object code to boot the ESP device and execute the AtomVM virtual machine code, which in turn is responsible for execution of an Erlang/Elixir application.

The AtomVM virtual machine is implemented in C, and the AtomVM binary image contains the binary object code compiled from C source files, as well as the ESP boot loader and partition map, which tells the ESP32 how the flash module is laid out.

AtomVM developers will typically write their applications in Erlang or Elixir. These source files are compiled into BEAM bytecode, which is then assembled into AtomVM “packbeam” (.avm) files. This packbeam file is flashed onto the ESP32 device, starting at the data partition address 0x210000. When AtomVM starts, it will look in this partition for the first occurrence of a BEAM module that exports a start/0 function. Once that module is located, execution of the BEAM bytecode will commence at that point.

The following diagram provides a simplified overview of the layout of the AtomVM virtual machine and Erlang/Elixir applications on the ESP32 flash module.

|               |
+---------------+  ----------- 0x1000
| boot loader   |           ^
+---------------+           |
| partition map |           | AtomVM
+---------------+           | binary
|               |           | image
|   AtomVM      |           |
|   Virtual     |           |
|   Machine     |           |
|               |           v
+---------------+  ----------- 0x210000
|               |           ^
|               |           |
|     data      |           | Erlang/Elixir
|   partition   |           | Application
|               |           |
|               |           v
+---------------+  ----------- end

Deploying an AtomVM application to an ESP32 device typically involved two steps:

Connecting the ESP32 device;

Deploying the AtomVM virtual machine;

Deploying an AtomVM application (typically an iterative process)

These steps are described in more detail below.

Connecting the ESP32 device

Connect the ESP32 to your development machine (e.g., laptop or PC) via a USB cable.

+---------------+
| laptop or PC  |
|               |           +-------+
|               | USB       |       |
|               x-----------x       |
|               |           |       |
|               |           +-------+
+---------------+           ESP32

Note. There are a wide variety of ESP32 modules, ranging from home-made breadboard solutions to all-in-one development boards. For simplicity, we assume a development board that can both be powered by a USB cable and which can be simultaneously flashed using the same cable, e.g., the Espressif ESP32 DevKit.

Consult your local development board documentation for instructions about how to connect your device to your development machine.

Deploying the AtomVM virtual machine

The following methods can be used to deploy the AtomVM virtual machine to an ESP32 device:

Flashing a binary image;

Building from source.

Flashing a binary images

Flashing the ESP32 using a pre-built binary image is by far the easiest path to getting started with development on the ESP32. Binary images contain the virtual machine image and all of the necessary components to run your application.

We recommend first erasing any existing applications on the ESP32 device. E.g.,

shell$ esptool.py --chip esp32 --port /dev/ttyUSB0 --baud 115200 erase_flash
...

Note. Specify the device port and baud settings and AtomVM image name to suit your particular environment.

Next, download the latest stable or nightly ESP32 release image from the AtomVM web site.

Note. Nightly images may be unstable and may result in unpredictable behavior.

Finally, use the esptool to flash the image to the start address 0x1000 on the ESP32. E.g.,

shell$ esptool.py --chip esp32 --port /dev/ttyUSB0 --baud 115200 \
    --before default_reset --after hard_reset \
    write_flash -u --flash_mode dio --flash_freq 40m --flash_size detect \
    0x1000 atomvm-esp32-v0.1.0.bin
...

Once completed, your ESP32 device is ready to run Erlang or Elixir programs targeted for AtomVM.

Building from source

You may optionally build AtomVM from source and deploy the AtomVM virtual machine to your ESP32 device manually. Building AtomVM from source is slightly more involved, as it requires the installation of the Espressif IDF SDK and tool chain and is typically recommended only for users who are doing development on the AtomVM virtual machine, or for developers implementing custom Nifs or ports.

Instructions for building AtomVM from source are covered in the AtomVM Build Instructions

Deploying an AtomVM application

An AtomVM application is a collection of BEAM files, which have been compiled using the Erlang or Elixir compiler. These BEAM files are assembled into an AtomVM “packbeam” (.avm) file, which in turn is flashed to the main data partition on the ESP32 flash module, starting at address 0x210000.

When the AtomVM virtual machine starts, it will search for the first module that contains an exported start/0 function in this partition, and it will begin execution of the BEAM bytecode at that function.

AtomVM applications can be written in Erlang or Elixir, or a combination of both. The AtomVM community has provided tooling for both platforms, making deployment of AtomVM applications as seamless as possible.

This section describes both Erlang and Elixir tooling for deploying AtomVM applications to ESP32 devices.

Erlang Tooling

Deployment of AtomVM applications written in the Erlang programming language is supported via the atomvm_rebar3_plugin plugin, a community-supported plugin to the rebar3 Erlang build tool.

You can generate a simple application from scratch using the atomvm_rebar3_plugin template, as follows:

Edit or create the $HOME/.config/rebar3/rebar.config file to include the atomvm_rebar3_plugin plugin:

%% $HOME/.config/rebar3/rebar.config
{plugins, [
    {atomvm_rebar3_plugin, "0.3.0"},
    ...
]}.

In any directory in which you have write permission, issue

shell$ rebar3 new atomvm_app <app-name>

where <app-name> is the name of the application you would like to create (e.g., myapp). This command will generate a rebar project under the directory <app-name>.

The generated application will contain the proper rebar.config configuration and will contain the <app-name>.erl module, which exports the start/0 function with a stubbed implementation.

Specifically, note the following stanza in the generated rebar.config file:

%% rebar.config
{plugins, [
    {atomvm_rebar3_plugin, "0.3.0"},
    ...
]}.

And note the myapp application exports a start/0 function, e.g.,

%% erlang
-module(myapp).
-export([start/0]).

start() ->
    ok.

With this plugin installed, you have access to the esp32_flash target, which will build an AtomVM packbeam

shell$ rebar3 esp32_flash --port /dev/ttyUSB0
===> Fetching atomvm_rebar3_plugin v0.3.0
===> Fetching rebar3_hex v6.11.3
===> Fetching hex_core v0.7.1
===> Fetching verl v1.0.2
===> Analyzing applications...
===> Compiling verl
===> Compiling hex_core
===> Compiling rebar3_hex
===> Fetching atomvm_packbeam v0.3.0
===> Analyzing applications...
===> Compiling atomvm_rebar3_plugin
===> Compiling packbeam
===> Verifying dependencies...
===> Analyzing applications...
===> Compiling myapp
===> AVM file written to : myapp.avm
===> esptool.py --chip esp32 --port /dev/ttyUSB0 --baud 115200 --before default_reset --after hard_reset write_flash -u --flash_mode dio --flash_freq 40m --flash_size detect 0x210000 /home/frege/myapp/_build/default/lib/myapp.avm

Note. Consult the the atomvm_rebar3_plugin plugin documentation, for more detailed information about how to use this tool.

Once the application has been flashed, you may connect to the ESP32 over the serial port using minicom, screen, or equivalent.

Elixir Tooling

TODO mix + https://github.com/atomvm/ExAtomVM + hex

Getting Started on the STM32 platform

TODO will se distribute a binary image for STM32?

Getting Started on the Generic UNIX platform

AtomVM may be run on UNIX-like platforms using the AtomVM executable.

You may specify one or more AVM files on the command line when running the AtomVM command. BEAM modules defined in earlier AVM modules on the command line take higher precedence that BEAM modules included in AVM files later in the argument list.

shell$ AtomVM /path/to/myapp.avm

Currently, the AtomVM executable must be built from source.

See the AtomVM Build Instructions for instructions about how to build AtomVM on the Generic UNIX platform.

Where to go from here

The following resources may be useful for understanding how to develop Erlang or Elixir applications for the AtomVM platform:

Example Programs

Programmers Guide

Packbeam Format

AtomVM makes use of the packbeam format for aggregating beam and other file types into a single file that is used as the code base for an AtomVM application. Typically, on an embedded device, packbeam files are uploaded (e.g., via serial connection) to a specific location on flash media. The AtomVM runtime will locate the entrypoint into the application, and use the beam and other files flashed to the local media to run the uploaded application.

AtomVM provides a simple tool for generating packbeam files, but other tools have emerged for manipulation packbeam files using standard Erlang and Elixir tool chains, notably Mix and rebar3.

This document describes the packbeam format, so that both AtomVM and upstream/downstream tooling have a reference document on which to base implementations.

Overview

Packbeam files are binary-encoded aggregations of BEAM and plain data files. At a high level, a packbeam file consists of a packbeam header, followed by a sequence of files (beam or otherwise), each of which is prefixed with a header, including data about the file (name, size, flags, etc).

All binary integer values are 32-bit, in network order (big-endian). Headers and encoded files are padded when necessary and aligned on 4-byte boundaries.

At present, the AtomVM runtime treats data in packbeam files as read-only data. There is no support for modifying the contents on an AtomVM file by the runtime.

Packbeam Header

All AtomVM files begin with the packbeam header, a fixed 24-byte sequence of octets:

0x23, 0x21, 0x2f, 0x75,
0x73, 0x72, 0x2f, 0x62,
0x69, 0x6e, 0x2f, 0x65,
0x6e, 0x76, 0x20, 0x41,
0x74, 0x6f, 0x6d, 0x56,
0x4d, 0x0a, 0x00, 0x00

The ASCII encoding of this sequence is

#!/usr/bin/env AtomVM\n

followed by two nil (0x00) bytes.

The packbeam header is followed by a sequence of 0 or more encoded files. The number of files in a packbeam file is not indicated in the packbeam header; however, packbeam files do contain a special end file header, marking the end of the sequence of encoded files.

File encodings

Each embedded file in a packbeam file contains a file header, followed by the file contents.

File Header

The file header consists of the following 4 fields:

size (32 bit, big-endian)

flags (32-bit, big endian)

reserved (32-bit, big-endian, currently unused)

module_name (null-terminated sequence of bytes)

The size field indicates the size (in bytes) of the encoded file following the header. This size includes the file content length, in addition to any padding that may have been added to the file, in order for it to align on a 4-byte boundary.

Currently, the two low-order bits of the flags field are used. 0x02 indicates the file is a BEAM file, and 0x01 indicates that the file contains a start/0 function, and is therefore suitable as an entrypoint to start code execution.

When AtomVM starts, it will scan the BEAM files in the AtomVM file, from start to finish, with which it is initialized to find the entrypoint to start code execution. It will start execution on the first BEAM file with a start/0 function, i.e., whose flags mask against 0x03. It is conventional, but not required, for the first file in an AtomVM file to be a BEAM file that has a start/0 entrypoint.

The reserved field is currently unused.

The module_name is variable length, null terminated sequence of characters. Because the module name is variable-length, the header may be padded with null characters (0x00), in order to align the start of the file contents on a 4-byte boundary.

Example

The following BEAM header indicates a BEAM file with a length of 308 bytes (0x00000134), with a start/0 entrypoint (0x00000003), and named mylib.beam (0x6D796C69 622E6265 616D00). The header has a 1-byte padding of null (0x00) characters.

00000134 00000003 00000000 6D796C69 622E6265 616D0000

BEAM files

BEAM files obey IFF encoding as detailed here, but certain information in BEAM files is stripped out in order to minimize the amount of data stored on flash.

The following BEAM chunks are included in BEAM files:

AtU8

Code

ExpT

LocT

ImpT

LitU

FunT

StrT

LitT

Any other chunks are stripped out of the BEAM files before insertion into AVM files.

In addition, data in the literals table (LitT) are uncompressed before insertion into AVM files, as the AtomVM runtime does not include support for zlib decompression.

BEAM files may be padded at the end with a sequence of 1-3 null (0x00) characters, in order to align on 4-byte boundaries.

Note. The module_name field in the file header will only contain the “base” name of the BEAM file, i.e., the file name stripped of any path information.

Normal Files

Normal files (e.g., text files, data files, etc.) can be stored in packbeam AVM files, as well as BEAM files. For example, a normal file might contain static configuration information, or data that is interpreted at runtime.

Normal files contain a 32-bit big-endian size prefix, indicating the size of the file data (without padding). Note that the size field in the file header includes the size of the data with padding, if applicable.

The AtomVM runtime provides access to data files via the atomvm:read_priv/2 NIF. This function will create a path name formed by the App (atom) and Path (string) terms provided by this function, separated by "/priv/". For example, the expression

atomvm:read_priv(mylib, "sample.txt")

yields a binary containing the contents of mylib/priv/sample.txt, if it exists, in the AtomVM packbeam file.

As a consequence, normal files should be included in packbeam files using module names that obey the above patterns.

Note. Normal file names may encode virtual directory names, such as mylib/priv/another/sample/text/file. There is no requirement that the Path component of a normal file be a simple file name.

end file

Packbeam files end with a special end header. The size field of the end header is 0 bytes.

Example

The following sequence of bytes encodes the end header:

00000000 00000000 00000000 656E6400

Programmers Guide

This guide is intended for programmers who develop applications targeted for AtomVM.

As an implementation of the Erlang virtual machine, AtomVM is designed to execute unmodified byte-code instructions compiled into BEAM files, either by the Erlang or Elixir compilers. This allow developers to write programs in their BEAM programming language of choice, and to use the common Erlang community tool-chains specific to their language platform, and to then deploy those applications onto the various devices that AtomVM supports.

This document describes the development workflow when writing AtomVM applications, as well as a high-level overview of the various APIs that are supported by AtomVM. With an understanding of this guide, you should be able to design, implement, and deploy applications onto a device running the AtomVM virtual machine.

AtomVM Features

Currently, AtomVM implements a strict subset of the BEAM instruction set, as of Erlang/OTP R21. Previous versions of Erlang/OTP are not supported.

A high level overview of the supported language features include:

All the major Erlang types, including

integers (with size limits)

limited support for floats (not supported on all platforms)

tuples

lists

binaries

maps

support for many Erlang BIFs and guard expressions to support the above types

pattern matching (case statements, function clause heads, etc)

try ... catch ... finally constructs

anonymous functions

process spawn and spawn_link

send (!) and receive messages

bit syntax (with some restrictions)

reference counted binaries

In addition, several features are supported specifically for integration with micro-controllers, including:

Wifi networking (network)

UDP and TCP/IP support (inet, gen_tcp and gen_udp)

Peripheral and system support on micro-controllers, including

GPIO, including pins reads, writes, and interrupts

I2C interface

SPI interface

UART interface

LEDC (PWM)

non-volatile storage (NVS)

deep sleep

Limitations

While the list of supported features is long and growing, the currently unsupported Erlang/OTP and BEAM features include (but are not limited to):

Bingnums. Integer values are restricted to 64-bit values.

SMP support. The AtomVM VM is currently a single-threaded process.

The epmd and the disterl protocols are not supported.

There is no support for code hot swapping.

There is no support for a Read-Eval-Print-Loop. (REPL)

Numerous modules and functions from Erlang/OTP standard libraries (kernel, stdlib, sasl, etc) are not implemented.

AtomVM bit syntax is restricted to alignment on 8-bit boundaries. Little-endian and signed insertion and extraction of integer values is restricted to 8, 16, and 32-bit values. Only unsigned big and little endian 64-bit values can be inserted into or extracted from binaries.

It is highly unlikely that an existing Erlang program targeted for Erlang/OTP will run unmodified on AtomVM. And indeed, even as AtomVM matures and additional features are added, it is more likely than not that Erlang applications will need to targeted specifically for the AtomVM platform. The intended target environment (small, cheap micro-controllers) differs enough from desktop or server-class systems in both scale and APIs that special care and attention is needed to target applications for such embedded environments.

That being said, many of the features of the BEAM are supported and provide a rich and compelling development environment for embedded devices, which Erlang and Elixir developers will find natural and productive.

AtomVM Development

This section describes the typical development environment and workflow most AtomVM developers are most likely to use.

Development Environment

In general, for most development purposes, you should be able to get away with an Erlang/OTP development environment (OTP21 or later), and for Elixir developers, and Elixir version TODO development environment. We assume most development will take place on some UNIX-like environment (e.g., Linux, FreeBSD, or MacOS). Consult your local package manager for installation of these development environments.

Developers will want to make use of common Erlang or Elixir development tools, such as rebar3 for Erlang developers or mix for Elixir developers.

Developers will need to make use of some AtomVM tooling. Fortunately, there are several choices for developers to use:

AtomVM PackBEAM executable (described below)

atomvm_rebar3_plugin, for Erlang development using rebar3.

ExAtomVM Mix plugin, Elixir development using Mix.

Some testing can be performed on UNIX-like systems, using the AtomVM executable that is suitable for your development environment. AtomVM applications that do not make use of platform-specific APIs are suitable for such tests.

Deployment and testing on micro-controllers is slightly more involved, as these platforms require additional hardware and software, described below.

ESP32 Deployment Requirements

In order to deploy AtomVM applications to and test on the ESP32 platform, developers will need:

A computer running MacOS or Linux (Windows support is TBD);

An ESP32 module with a USB/UART connector (typically part of an ESP32 development board);

A USB cable capable of connecting the ESP32 module or board to your development machine (laptop or PC);

The esptool program, for flashing the AtomVM image and AtomVM programs;

(Optional, but recommended) A serial console program, such as minicom or screen, so that you can view console output from your AtomVM application.

STM32 Deployment Requirements

TODO

Development Workflow

For the majority of users, AtomVM applications are written in the Erlang or Elixir programming language. These applications are compiled to BEAM (.beam) files using standard Erlang or Elixir compiler tool chains (erlc, rebar, mix, etc). The generated BEAM files contain byte-code that can be executed by the Erlang/OTP runtime, or by the AtomVM virtual machine.

Note. In a small number of cases, it may be useful to write parts of an application in the C programming language, as AtomVM nifs or ports. However, writing AtomVM nifs and ports is outside of the scope of this document.

Once Erlang and/or Elixir files are compiled to BEAM files, AtomVM provides tooling for processing and aggregating BEAM files into AtomVM Packbeam (.avm) files, using AtomVM tooling, distributed as part of AtomVM, or as provided through the AtomVM community.

AtomVM packbeam files are the applications and libraries that run on the AtomVM virtual machine. For micro-controller devices, they are “flashed” or uploaded to the device; for command-line use of AtomVM (e.g., on Linux, FreeBSD, or MacOS), they are supplied as the first parameter to the AtomVM command.

The following diagram illustrates the typical development workflow, starting from Erlang or Elixir source code, and resulting in a deployed Packbeam file:

*.erl or *.ex                  *.beam
+-------+                   +-------+
|       |+                  |       |+
|       ||+                 |       ||+
|       |||     -------->   |       |||
|       |||  Erlang/Elixir  |       |||
+-------+||     Compiler    +-------+||
 +-------+|                  +-------+|
  +-------+                   +-------+
     ^                           |
     |                           | packbeam
     |                           |
     |                           v
     |                       +-------+
     |                       |       |
     | test                  |       |
     | debug                 |       |
     | fix                   |       |
     |                       +-------+
     |                        app.avm
     |                           |
     |                           | flash/upload
     |                           |
     |                           v
     +-------------------- Micro-controller
                              device

The typical compile-test-debug cycle can be summarized in the following steps:

Deploy the AtomVM virtual machine to your device

Develop an AtomVM application in Erlang or Elixir

Write application

Deploy application to device

Test/Debug/Fix application

Repeat

Deployment of the AtomVM virtual machine and an AtomVM application currently require a USB serial connection. There is currently no support for over-the-air (OTA) updates.

For more information about deploying the AtomVM image and AtomVM applications to your device, see the Getting Started Guide

Applications

An AtomVM application is a collection of BEAM files, aggregated into an AtomVM “Packbeam” (.avm) file, and typically deployed (flashed) to some device. These BEAM files be be compiled from Erlang, Elixir, or any other language that targets the Erlang VM.

Note. The return value from the start/0 function is ignored.

Here, for example is one of the smallest AtomVM applications you can write:

%% erlang
-module(myapp).

-export([start/0]).

start() ->
    ok.

This particular application doesn’t do much, of course. The application will start and immediately terminate, with a return value of ok. Typical AtomVM applications will be more complex than this one, and the AVM file that contains the application BEAM files will be considerably larger and more complex than the above program.

Most applications will spawn processes, send and receive messages between processes, and wait for certain conditions to apply before terminating, if they terminate at all. For applications that spawn processes and run forever, you may need to add an empty receive ... end block, to prevent the AtomVM from terminating prematurely, e.g.,

%% erlang
wait_forever() ->
    receive X -> X end.

Packbeam files

AtomVM applications are packaged into Packbeam (.avm) files, which contain collections of files, typically BEAM (.beam) files that have been generated by the Erlang or Elixir compiler.

At least one BEAM module in this file must contain an exported start/0 function. The first module in a Packbeam file that contain this function is the entry-point of your application and will be executed when the AtomVM virtual machine starts.

Not all files in a Packbeam need to be BEAM modules – you can embed any type of file in a Packbeam file, for consumption by your AtomVM application.

Note. The Packbeam format is described in more detail in the AtomVM PackBEAM format.

The AtomVM community has provided several tools for simplifying your experience, as a developer. These tools allow you to use standard Erlang and Elixir tooling (such as rebar3 and mix) to build Packbeam files and deploy then to your device of choice.

PackBEAM tool

The PackBEAM tool is a command-line application that can be used to create Packbeam files from a collection of input files:

shell$ PackBEAM -h
Usage: PackBEAM [-h] [-l] <avm-file> [<options>]
    -h                                                Print this help menu.
    -l <input-avm-file>                               List the contents of an AVM file.
    [-a] <output-avm-file> <input-beam-or-avm-file>+  Create an AVM file (archive if -a specified).

To create a packbeam file, specify the name of the AVM file to created (by convention, ending in .avm), followed by a list of BEAM files:

shell$ PackBEAM foo.avm path/to/foo.beam path/to/bar.beam

You can also specify another AVM file to include. Thus, for example, to add to BEAM file to an existing AVM file, you might enter:

shell$ PackBEAM foo.avm foo.avm path/to/gnu.beam

To list the contents of an AVM file, use the -l flag:

shell% PackBEAM -l foo.avm
foo.beam *
bar.beam
gnu.beam

Any BEAM files that export a start/0 function will contain an asterisk (*) in the AVM file contents.

Running AtomVM

AtomVM is executed in different ways, depending on the platform. On most microcontrollers (e.g., the ESP32), the VM starts when the device is powered on. On UNIX platforms, the VM is started from the command-line using the AtomVM executable.

AtomVM will use the first module in the supplied AVM file that exports a start/0 function as the entrypoint for the application.

AtomVM program syntax

On UNIX platforms, you can specify a BEAM file or AVM file as the first argument to the executable, e.g.,

shell$ AtomVM foo.avm

Note. If you start the AtomVM executable with a BEAM file, then the corresponding module may not make any calls to external function in other modules, with the exception of built-in functions and Nifs that are included in the VM.

Core APIs

The AtomVM virtual machine provides a set of Erlang built-in functions (BIFs) and native functions (NIFs), as well as a collection of Erlang and Elixir libraries that can be used from your applications.

This section provides an overview of these APIs. For more detailed information about specific APIs, please consult the API reference documentation.

Standard Libraries

AtomVM provides a limited implementations of standard library modules, including:

base64

gen_server

gen_statem

io and io_lib

lists

maps

proplists

supervisor

timer

In addition AtomVM provides limited implementations of standard Elixir modules, including:

List

Tuple

Enum

Kernel

Module

Process

Console

For detailed information about these functions, please consult the API reference documentation. These modules provide a strict subset of functionality from their Erlang/OTP counterparts. However, they aim to be API-compatible with the Erlang/OTP interfaces, at least for the subset of provided functionality.

Console Output

There are several mechanisms for writing data to the console.

For common debugging, many users will find erlang:display/1 sufficient for debugging:

%% erlang
erlang:display({foo, [{bar, tapas}]}).

The output parameter is any Erlang term, and a newline will be appended automatically.

Users may prefer using the io:format/1,2 functions for more controlled output:

%% erlang
io:format("The ~p did a ~p~n", [friddle, frop]).

Note that the io_lib module can be used to format string data, as well.

Note. Formatting parameters are currently limited to ~p, ~s, and ~n.

Process Management

You can obtain a list of all processes in the system via erlang:processes/0:

%% erlang
Pids = erlang:processes().

And for each process, you can get detailed process information via the erlang:process_info/1 function:

%% erlang
[io:format("Process info for Pid ~p: ~p~n", [Pid, erlang:process_info(Pid)]) || Pid <- Pids].

The return value is a property list containing values for heap_size, stack_size, message_queue_len,and memory consumed by the process.

System APIs

You can obtain system information about the AtomVM virtual machine via the erlang:system_info/1 function, which takes an atom parameter designating the desired datum. Allowable parameters include

process_count The number of processes running in the system.

port_count The number of ports running in the system.

atom_count The number of atoms allocated in the system.

word_size The word size (in bytes) on the current platform (typically 4 or 8).

For example,

%% erlang
io:format("Atom Count: ~p~n", [erlang:system_info(atom_count)]).

Note. Additional platform-specific information is supported, depending on the platform type. See below.

Use the atomvm:platform/0 to obtain the system platform on which your code is running. The return value of this function is an atom who’s value will depend on the platform on which your application is running.

%% erlang
case atomvm:platform() of
    esp32 ->
        io:format("I am running on an ESP32!~n");
    stm32 ->
        io:format("I am running on an STM32!~n");
    generic_unix ->
        io:format("I am running on a UNIX box!~n")
end.

Use erlang:garbage_collect/0 or erlang:garbage_collect/1 to force the AtomVM garbage collector to run on a give process. Garbage collection will in general happen automatically when additional free space is needed and is rarely needed to be called explicitly.

The 0-arity version of this function will run the garbage collector on the currently executing process.

%% erlang
Pid = ... %% get a reference to some pid
ok = erlang:garbage_collect(Pid).

System Time

AtomVM supports numerous function for accessing the current time on the device.

Use erlang:timestamp/0 to get the current time since the UNIX epoch (Midnight, Jan 1, 1970, UTC), at microsecond granularity, expressed as a triple (mega-seconds, seconds, and micro-seconds):

%% erlang
{MegaSecs, Secs, MicroSecs} = erlang:timestamp().

User erlang:system_time/1 to obtain the seconds or milliseconds since the UNIX epoch (Midnight, Jan 1, 1970, UTC):

%% erlang
Seconds = erlang:system_time(second).
MilliSeconds = erlang:system_time(millisecond).

Use erlang:universaltime/0 to get the current time at second resolution, to obtain the year, month, day, hour, minute, and second:

%% erlang
{{Year, Month, Day}, {Hour, Minute, Second}} = erlang:universaltime().

Note. Setting the system time is done in a platform-specific manner. For information about how to set system time on the ESP32, see the Network Programming Guide.

Miscellaneous

Use the erlang:md5/1 function to compute the MD5 hash of an input binary. The output is a fixed-length binary ()

%% erlang
Hash = erlang:md5(<<foo>>).

Use atomvm:random/0 to generate a random unsigned 32-bit integer in the range 0..4294967295:

%% erlang
RandomInetger = atomvm:random().

Use atomvm:random_bytes/1 to return a randomly populated binary of a specified size:

%% erlang
RandomBinary = erlang:random_bytes(32).

Use base64:encode/1 and base64:decode/1 to encode to and decode from Base64 format. The input value to these functions may be a binary or string. The output value from these functions is an Erlang binary.

%% erlang
Encoded = base64:encode(<<"foo">>).
<<"foo">> = base64:decode(Encoded).

You can Use base64:encode_to_string/1 and base64:decode_to_string/1 to perform the same encoding, but to return values as Erlang list structures, instead of as binaries.

ESP32-specific APIs

Certain APIs are specific to and only supported on the ESP32 platform. This section describes these APIs.

System-Level APIs

As noted above, the erlang:system_info/1 function can be used to obtain system-specific information about the platform on which your application is deployed.

You can request ESP32-specific information using using the following input atoms:

esp_free_heap_size Returns the available free space in the ESP32 heap

esp_chip_info Returns 4-tuple of the form {esp32, Features, Cores, Revision}, where Features is a bit mask of features enabled in the chip, Cores is the number of CPU cores on the chip, and Revision is the chip version.

esp_idf_version Return the IDF SDK version, as a string.

For example,

%% erlang
FreeHeapSize = erlang:system_info(esp_free_heap_size).

Non-volatile Storage

AtomVM provides functions for setting, retrieving, and deleting key-value data in binary form in non-volatile storage (NVS) on an ESP device. Entries in NVS survive reboots of the ESP device, and can be used a limited “persistent store” for key-value data.

Note. NVS storage is limited in size, and NVS keys are restricted to 15 characters. Try to avoid writing frequently to NVS storage, as the flash storage may degrade more rapidly with repeated writes to the medium.

NVS entries are stored under a namespace and key, both of which are expressed as atoms. AtomVM uses the namespace atomvm for entries under its control. Applications may read from and write to the atomvm namespace, but they are strongly discouraged from doing so, except when explicitly stated otherwise.

To set a value in non-volatile storage, use the esp:set_binary/3 function, and specify a namespace, key, and value:

%% erlang
Namespace = <<"my-namespace">>,
Key = <<"my-key">>,
esp:set_binary(Namespace, Key, <<"some-value">>).

To retrieve a value in non-volatile storage, use the esp:get_binary/2 function, and specify a namespace and key. You can optionally specify a default value (of any desired type), if an entry does not exist in non-volatile storage:

%% erlang
Value = esp:get_binary(Namespace, Key, <<"default-value">>).

To delete an entry, use the esp:erase_key/2 function, and specify a namespace and key:

%% erlang
ok = esp:erase_key(Namespace, Key).

You can delete all entries in a namespace via the esp:erase_all/1 function:

%% erlang
ok = esp:erase_all(Namespace).

Finally, you can delete all entries in all namespaces on the NVS partition via the esp:reformat/0 function:

%% erlang
ok = esp:reformat().

Applications should use the esp:reformat/0 function with caution, in case other applications are making using the non-volatile storage.

Note. NVS entries are currently stored in plaintext and are not encrypted. Applications should exercise caution if sensitive security information, such as account passwords, are stored in NVS storage.

Restart and Deep Sleep

You can use the esp:restart/0 function to immediately restart the ESP32 device. This function does not return a value.

%% erlang
esp:restart().

Use the esp:reset_reason/0 function to obtain the reason for the ESP32 restart. Possible values include:

esp_rst_unknown

esp_rst_poweron

esp_rst_ext

esp_rst_sw

esp_rst_panic

esp_rst_int_wdt

esp_rst_task_wdt

esp_rst_wdt

esp_rst_deepsleep

esp_rst_brownout

esp_rst_sdio

Use the esp:deep_sleep/1 function to put the ESP device into deep sleep for a specified number of milliseconds. Be sure to safely stop any critical processes running before this function is called, as it will cause an immediate shutdown of the device.

%% erlang
esp:deep_sleep(60*1000).

Use the esp:sleep_get_wakeup_cause/0 function can be used to inspect the reason for a wakeup. Currently, the only supported return value is the atom undefined or sleep_wakeup_timer.

%% erlang
case esp:sleep_get_wakeup_cause() of
    sleep_wakeup_timer ->
        io:format("Woke up from a timer~n");
    _ ->
        io:format("Woke up for some other reason~n")
end.

Miscellaneous

The freq_hz function can be used to retrieve the clock frequency of the chip.

esp:freq_hz/0

Peripherals

The AtomVM virtual machine and libraries support APIs for interfacing with peripheral devices connected to the ESP32. This section provides information about these APIs.

GPIO

You can read and write digital values on GPIO pins using the gpio module, using the digital_read/1 and digital_write/2 functions. You must first set the direction of the pin using the gpio:set_direction/2 function, using input or output as the direction parameter.

To read the value of a GPIO pin (high or low), use gpio:digital_read/1:

%% erlang
Pin = 2,
gpio:set_direction(Pin, input),
case gpio:digital_read(Pin) of
    high ->
        io:format("Pin ~p is high ~n", [Pin]);
    low ->
        io:format("Pin ~p is low ~n", [Pin])
end.

To set the value of a GPIO pin (high or low), use gpio:digital_write/2:

%% erlang
Pin = 2,
gpio:set_direction(Pin, output),
gpio:digital_write(Pin, low).

Interrupt Handling

You can get notified of changes in the state of a GPIO pin by using the gpio:set_int/2 function. This function takes a reference to a GPIO Pin and a trigger. Allowable triggers are rising, falling, both, low, high, and none (to disable an interrupt).

When a trigger event occurs, such as a pin rising in voltage, a tuple will be delivered to the process containing the atom gpio_interrupt and the pin.

%% erlang
Pin = 2,
gpio:set_direction(Pin, input),
GPIO = gpio:open(),
ok = gpio:set_int(GPIO, Pin, rising),
receive
    {gpio_interrupt, Pin} ->
        io:format("Pin ~p is rising ~n", [Pin])
end.

Interrupts can be removed by using the gpio:remove_int/2 function.

I2C

The i2c module encapsulates functionality associated with the 2-wire Inter-Integrated Circuit (I2C) interface.

Note. Information about the ESP32 I2C interface can be found in the IDF SDK I2C Documentation.

The AtomVM I2C implementation uses the AtomVM Port mechanism and must be initialized using the i2c:open/1 function. The single parameter contains a properties list, with the following elements:

Key

|

Value Type

|

Required

|

Description

scl_io_num

|

integer()

|

yes

|

I2C clock pin (SCL)

sda_io_num

|

integer()

|

yes

|

I2C data pin (SDA)

i2c_clock_hz

|

integer()

|

yes

|

I2C clock frequency (in hertz)

For example,

%% erlang
I2C = i2c:open([
    {scl_io_num, 21}, {sda_io_num, 22}, {i2c_clock_hz, 40000}
])

Once the port is opened, you can use the returned I2C instance to read and write bytes to the attached device.

Both read and write operations require the I2C bus address from which data is read or to which data is written. A devices address is typically hard-wired for the specific device type, or in some cases may be changed by the addition or removal of a resistor.

In addition, you may optionally specify a register to read from or write to, as some devices require specification of a register value. Consult your device’s data sheet for more information and the device’s I2C bus address and registers, if applicable.

There are two patterns for writing data to an I2C device:

Queuing i2c:qwrite_bytes/2,3 write operations between calls to i2c:begin_transmission/1 and i2c:end_transmission/1. In this case, write operations are queued locally and dispatched to the target device when the i2c:end_transmission/1 operation is called;

Writing a byte or sequence of bytes in one i2c:write_bytes/2,3 operation.

The choice of which pattern to use will depend on the device being communicated with. For example, some devices require a sequence of write operations to be queued and written in one atomic write, in which case the first pattern is appropriate. E.g.,

%% erlang
ok = i2c:begin_transmission(I2C),
ok = i2c:qwrite_bytes(I2C, DeviceAddress, Register1, <<"some sequence of bytes">>),
ok = i2c:qwrite_bytes(I2C, DeviceAddress, Register2, <<"some other of bytes">>),
ok = i2c:end_transmission(I2C),

In other cases, you may just need to write a byte or sequence of bytes in one operation to the device:

%% erlang
ok = i2c:write_bytes(I2C, DeviceAddress, Register1, <<"write it all in one go">>),

Reading bytes is more straightforward. Simply use i2c:read_bytes/3,4, specifying the port instance, device address, optionally a register, and the number of bytes to read:

%% erlang
BinaryData = i2c:read_bytes(I2C, DeviceAddress, Register, Len)

SPI

The spi module encapsulates functionality associated with the 4-wire Serial Peripheral Interface (SPI) in leader mode.

Note. Information about the ESP32 SPI leader mode interface can be found in the IDF SDK SPI Documentation.

The AtomVM SPI implementation uses the AtomVM Port mechanism and must be initialized using the spi:open/1 function. The single parameter to this function is a properties list containing two elements:

bus_config – a properties list containing entries for the SPI bus

device_config – a properties list containing entries for the device

The bus_config properties list contains the following entries:

Key

|

Value Type

|

Required

|

Description

miso_io_num

|

integer()

|

yes

|

SPI leader-in, follower-out pin (MOSI)

mosi_io_num

|

integer()

|

yes

|

SPI leader-out, follower-in pin (MISO)

sclk_io_num

|

integer()

|

yes

|

SPI clock pin (SCLK)

The device_config – a properties list containing entries for the device properties list contains the following entries:

Key

|

Value Type

|

Required

|

Description

spi_clock_hz

|

integer()

|

yes

|

SPI clock frequency (in hertz)

spi_mode

|

integer()

|

yes

|

SPI mode

spi_cs_io_num

|

integer()

|

yes

|

SPI chip select pin (CS)

address_len_bits

|

integer()

|

yes

|

number of bits in a read/write operation (for example, 8, to read and write single bytes at a time)

For example,

%% erlang
SPIConfig = [
    {bus_config, [
        {miso_io_num, 12},
        {mosi_io_num, 13},
        {sclk_io_num, 14}
    ]},
    {device_config, [
        {spi_clock_hz, 1000000},
        {spi_mode, 0},
        {spi_cs_io_num, 18},
        {address_len_bits, 8}
    ]}
],
SPI = spi:open(SPIConfig),
...

Once the port is opened, you can use the returned SPI instance to read and write bytes to the attached device.

To read a byte at a given address on the device, use the spi:read_at/3 function:

%% erlang
{ok, Byte} = spi:read_at(SPI, Address, 8)

To write a byte at a given address on the device, use the spi_write_at/4 function:

%% erlang
write_at(SPI, Address, 8, Byte)

Note. The spi:write_at/4 takes integer values as inputs and the spi:read_at/3 returns integer values. You may read and write up to 32-bit integer values via these functions.

Consult your local device data sheet for information about various device addresses to read from or write to, and their semantics.

UART

The uart module encapsulates functionality associated with the Universal Asynchronous Receiver/Transmitter (UART) interface supported on ESP32 devices. Some devices, such as NMEA GPS receivers, make use of this interface for communicating with an ESP32.

Note. Information about the ESP32 UART interface can be found in the IDF SDK UART Documentation.

The AtomVM UART implementation uses the AtomVM Port mechanism and must be initialized using the uart:open/2 function.

The first parameter indicates the ESP32 UART hardware interface. Legal values are:

"UART0" | "UART1" | "UART2"

The selection of the hardware interface dictates the default RX and TX pins on the ESP32:

Port

|

RX pin

|

TX pin

UART0

|

GPIO_3

|

GPIO_1

UART1

|

GPIO_9

|

GPIO_10

UART2

|

GPIO_16

|

GPIO_17

The second parameter is a properties list, containing the following elements:

Key

|

Value Type

|

Required

|

Default Value

|

Description

speed

|

integer()

|

no

|

115200

|

UART baud rate (bits/sec)

data_bits

|

5 | 6 | 7 | 8

|

no

|

8

|

UART data bits

stop_bits

|

1 | 2

|

no

|

1

|

UART stop bits

flow_control

|

hardware | software | none

|

no

|

none

|

Flow control

parity

|

even | odd | none

|

no

|

none

|

UART parity check

For example,

%% erlang
UART = uart:open("UART0", [{speed, 9600}])

Once the port is opened, you can use the returned UART instance to read and write bytes to the attached device.

To read data from the UART channel, use the uart:read/1 function. The return value from this function is a binary:

%% erlang
Bin = uart:read(UART)

To write data to the UART channel, use the uart_write/2 function. The input data is any Erlang I/O list:

%% erlang
uart:write(UART, [<<"any">>, $d, $a, $t, $a, "goes", <<"here">>])

Consult your local device data sheet for information about the format of data to be read from or written to the UART channel.

LED Control

The LED Control API can be used to drive LEDs, as well as generate PWM signals on GPIO pins.

The LEDC API is encapsulated in the ledc module and is a direct translation of the IDF SDK LEDC API, with a natural mapping into Erlang. This API is intended for users with complex use-cases, and who require low-level access to the LEDC APIs.

The ledc.hrl module should be used for common modes, channels, duty cycle resolutions, and so forth.

%% erlang
-include("ledc.hrl").

...

%% create a 5khz timer
SpeedMode = ?LEDC_HIGH_SPEED_MODE,
Channel = ?LEDC_CHANNEL_0,
ledc:timer_config([
    {duty_resolution, ?LEDC_TIMER_13_BIT},
    {freq_hz, 5000},
    {speed_mode, ?LEDC_HIGH_SPEED_MODE},
    {timer_num, ?LEDC_TIMER_0}
]).

%% bind pin 2 to this timer in a channel
ledc:channel_config([
    {channel, Channel},
    {duty, 0},
    {gpio_num, 2},
    {speed_mode, ?LEDC_HIGH_SPEED_MODE},
    {hpoint, 0},
    {timer_sel, ?LEDC_TIMER_0}
]).

%% set the duty cycle to 0, and fade up to 16000 over 5 seconds
ledc:set_duty(SpeedMode, Channel, 0).
ledc:update_duty(SpeedMode, Channel).
TargetDuty = 16000.
FadeMs = 5000.
ok = ledc:set_fade_with_time(SpeedMode, Channel, TargetDuty, FadeMs).

Protocols

AtomVM supports network programming on devices that support it, specifically the ESP32 platform, with its built-in support for WIFI networking, and of course on the UNIX platform.

This section describes the network programming APIs available on AtomVM.

Network (ESP32 only)

The ESP32 supports WiFi connectivity as part of the built-in WiFi and Bluetooth radio (and in most modules, an integrated antenna). The WIFI radio on an ESP32 can operate in several modes:

STA (Station) mode, whereby it acts as a member of an existing WiFi network;

AP (Access Point) mode, whereby the ESP32 acts as an access point for other devices; or

AP+STA mode, whereby the ESP32 behaves both as a member of an existing WiFi network and as an access point for other devices.

AtomVM supports these modes of operation via the network module, which is used to initialize the network and allow applications to respond to events within the network, such as a network disconnect or reconnect, or a connection to the ESP32 from another device.

Note. Establishment and maintenance of network connections on roaming devices is a complex and subtle art, and the AtomVM network module is designed to accommodate as many IoT scenarios as possible. This section of the programmer’s guide is deliberately brief and only addresses the most basic scenarios. For a more detailed explanation of the AtomVM network module and its many use-cases, please refer to the AtomVM Network Programming Guide.

STA mode

To connect your ESP32 to an existing WiFi network, use the network:wait_for_sta/1,2 convenience function, which abstracts away some of the more complex details of ESP32 STA mode.

This function takes a station mode configuration, as a properties list, and optionally a timeout (in milliseconds) before connecting to the network should fail. The default timeout, if unspecified, is 15 seconds.

The station mode configuration supports the following options:

Key

|

Value Type

|

Required

|

Default Value

|

Description

ssid

|

string() | binary()

|

yes

|

-

|

WiFi AP SSID

psk

|

string() | binary()

|

yes, if network is encrypted

|

-

|

WiFi AP password

dhcp_hostname

|

string() | binary()

|

no

|

atomvm-<MAC> where <MAC> is the factory-assigned MAC-address of the device

|

DHCP hostname for the connecting device

Note. The WiFi network to which you are connecting must support DHCP and IPv4. IPv6 addressing is not yet supported on AtomVM.

If the ESP32 device connects to the specified network successfully, the device’s assigned address, netmask, and gateway address will be returned in an {ok, ...} tuple; otherwise, an error is returned.

For example:

%% erlang
Config = [
    {ssid, <<"myssid">>},
    {psk,  <<"mypsk">>},
    {dhcp_hostname, <<"mydevice">>}
],
case network:wait_for_sta(Config, 15000) of
    {ok, {Address, _Netmask, _Gateway}} ->
        io:format("Acquired IP address: ~p~n", [Address]);
    {error, Reason} ->
        io:format("Network initialization failed: ~p~n", [Reason])
end

Once connected to a WiFi network, you may begin TCP or UDP networking, as described in more detail below.

For information about how to handle disconnections and reconnections to a WiFi network, see the AtomVM Network Programming Guide.

AP mode

To turn your ESP32 into an access point for other devices, you can use the network:wait_for_ap/1,2 convenience function, which abstracts away some of the more complex details of ESP32 AP mode. When the network is started, the ESP32 device will assign itself the 192.168.4.1 address. Any devices that connect to the ESP32 will take addresses in the 192.168.4/24 network.

This function takes an access point mode configuration, as a properties list, and optionally a timeout (in milliseconds) before starting the network should fail. The default timeout, if unspecified, is 15 seconds.

The access point mode configuration supports the following options:

Key

|

Value Type

|

Required

|

Default Value

|

Description

ssid

|

string() | binary()

|

no

|

atomvm-<MAC> where <MAC> is the factory-assigned MAC-address of the device

|

WiFi AP SSID

ssid_hidden

|

boolean()

|

no

|

false

|

Whether the AP SSID should be hidden (i.e., not broadcast)

psk

|

string() | binary()

|

yes, if network is encrypted

|

-

|

WiFi AP password. Warning: If this option is not specified, the network will be an open network, to which anyone who knows the SSID can connect and which is not encrypted.

ap_max_connections

|

non_neg_integer()

|

no

|

4

|

Maximum number of devices that can be connected to this AP

If the ESP32 device starts the AP network successfully, the ok atom is returned; otherwise, an error is returned.

For example:

%% erlang
Config = [
    {psk,  <<"mypsk">>}
],
case network:wait_for_ap(Config, 15000) of
    ok ->
        io:format("AP network started at 192.168.4.1~n");
    {error, Reason} ->
        io:format("Network initialization failed: ~p~n", [Reason])
end

Once the WiFi network is started, you may begin TCP or UDP networking, as described in more detail below.

For information about how to handle connections and disconnections from attached devices, see the AtomVM Network Programming Guide.

STA+AP mode

For information about how to run the AtomVM network in STA and AP mode simultaneously, see the AtomVM Network Programming Guide.

UDP

AtomVM supports network programming using the User Datagram Protocol (UDP) via the gen_udp module. This modules obeys the syntax and semantics of the Erlang/OTP gen_udp interface.

Note. Not all of the Erlang/OTP gen_udp functionality is implemented in AtomVM. For details, consults the AtomVM API documentation.

To open a UDP port, use the gen_udp:open/1,2 function. Supply a port number, and if your application plans to receive UDP messages, specify that the port is active via the {active, true} property in the optional properties list.

For example:

%% erlang
Port = 44404,
case gen_udp:open(Port, [{active, true}]) of
    {ok, Socket} ->
        {ok, SockName} = inet:sockname(Socket)
        io:format("Opened UDP socket on ~p.~n", [SockName])
    Error ->
        io:format("An error occurred opening UDP socket: ~p~n", [Error])
end

If the port is active, you can receive UDP messages in your application. They will be delivered as a 5-tuple, starting with the udp atom, and containing the socket, address and port from which the message was sent, as well as the datagram packet, itself, as a binary.

%% erlang
receive
    {udp, _Socket, Address, Port, Packet} ->
        io:format("Received UDP packet ~p from address ~p port ~p~n", [Packet, Address, Port)])
end,

With a reference to a UDP Socket, you can send messages to a target UDP endpoint using the gen_udp:send/4 function. Specify the UDP socket returned from gen_udp:open/1,2, the address (as a 4-tuple of octets), port number, and the datagram packet to send:

Packet = <<":アトムＶＭ">>,
Address = {192, 168, 1, 101},
Port = 44404,
case gen_udp:send(Socket, Address, Port, Packet) of
    ok ->
        io:format("Sent ~p~n", [Packet]);
    Error ->
        io:format("An error occurred sending a packet: ~p~n", [Error])
end

Note. IPv6 networking is not currently supported in AtomVM.

TCP

AtomVM supports network programming using the Transport Connection Protocol (TCP) via the gen_tcp module. This modules obeys the syntax and semantics of the Erlang/OTP gen_tcp interface.

Note. Not all of the Erlang/OTP gen_tcp functionality is implemented in AtomVM. For details, consults the AtomVM API documentation.

Server-side TCP

Server side TCP requires opening a listening socket, and then waiting to accept connections from remote clients. Once a connection is established, the application may then use a combination of sending and receiving packets over the established connection to or from the remote client.

Note. Programming TCP on the server-side using the gen_tcp interface is a subtle art, and this portion of the documentation will not go into all of the design choices available when designing a TCP application.

Start by opening a listening socket using the gen_tcp:listen/2 function. Specify the port number on which the TCP server should be listening:

%% erlang
case gen_tcp:listen(44405, []) of
    {ok, ListenSocket} ->
        {ok, SockName} = inet:sockname(Socket),
        io:format("Listening for connections at address ~p.~n", [SockName]),
        spawn(fun() -> accept(ListenSocket) end);
    Error ->
        io:format("An error occurred listening: ~p~n", [Error])
end.

In this particular example, the server will spawn a new process to wait to accept a connection from a remote client, by calling the gen_tcp:accept/1 function, passing in a reference to the listening socket. This function will block until a client has established a connection with the server.

When a client connects, the function will return a tuple {ok, Socket}, where Socket is a reference to the connection between the client and server:

%% erlang
accept(ListenSocket) ->
    io:format("Waiting to accept connection...~n"),
    case gen_tcp:accept(ListenSocket) of
        {ok, Socket} ->
            {ok, SockName} = inet:sockname(Socket),
            {ok, Peername} = inet:peername(Socket),
            io:format("Accepted connection.  local: ~p peer: ~p~n", [SockName, Peername]),
            spawn(fun() -> accept(ListenSocket) end),
            echo();
        Error ->
            io:format("An error occurred accepting connection: ~p~n", [Error])
    end.

Note that immediately after accepting a connection, this example code will spawn a new process to accept any new connections from other clients.

The socket returned from gen_tcp:accept/1 can then be used to send and receive messages to the connected client:

%% erlang
echo() ->
    io:format("Waiting to receive data...~n"),
    receive
        {tcp_closed, _Socket} ->
            io:format("Connection closed.~n"),
            ok;
        {tcp, Socket, Packet} ->
            {ok, Peername} = inet:peername(Socket),
            io:format("Received packet ~p from ~p.  Echoing back...~n", [Packet, Peername]),
            gen_tcp:send(Socket, Packet),
            echo()
    end.

In this case, the server program will continuosuly echo the received input back to the client, until the client closes the connection.

For more information about the gen_tcp server interface, consult the AtomVM API Reference Documentation.

Client-side TCP

Client side TCP requires establishing a connection with an endpoint, and then using a combination of sending and receiving packets over the established connection.

Start by opening a connection to another TCP endpoint using the gen_tcp:connect/3 function. Supply the address and port of the TCP endpoint.

For example:

%% erlang
Address = {192, 168, 1, 101},
Port = 44405,
case gen_tcp:connect(Address, Port, []) of
    {ok, Socket} ->
        {ok, SockName} = inet:sockname(Socket),
        {ok, Peername} = inet:peername(Socket),
        io:format("Connected to ~p from ~p~n", [Peername, SockName]);
    Error ->
        io:format("An error occurred connecting: ~p~n", [Error])
end

Once a connection is established, you can use a combination of

%% erlang
SendPacket = <<":アトムＶＭ">>,
case gen_tcp:send(Socket, SendPacket) of
    ok ->
        receive
            {tcp_closed, _Socket} ->
                io:format("Connection closed.~n"),
                ok;
            {tcp, _Socket, ReceivedPacket} ->
                {ok, Peername} = inet:peername(Socket),
                io:format("Received ~p from ~p~n", [ReceivedPacket, Peername])
        end;
    Error ->
        io:format("An error occurred sending a packet: ~p~n", [Error])
end.

For more information about the gen_tcp client interface, consults the AtomVM API documentation.

Welcome to AtomVM!

Welcome to AtomVM, the Erlang virtual machine for IoT devices!

What is AtomVM?

AtomVM is a ground-up implementation of the Bogdan Erlang Abstract Machine (a.k.a the BEAM) and is designed specifically to run on small systems, such as the Espressif ESP32 and ST Microelectronics STM32 micro-controllers. It allows developers to implement IoT applications in the Erlang or Elixir programming languages and to deploy those applications onto tiny devices. (Users may also target their applications for fully-fledged operating systems, such as Linux, FreeBSD, and MacOS, though in most cases deployment to traditional computers is done for development and testing purposes, only.)

AtomVM features include:

An Erlang runtime, capable of executing bytecode instructions in compiled BEAM files;

Support for all the major Erlang and Elixir types, including integers, strings, lists, maps, binaries, Enums, and more;

A memory-managed environment, with efficient garbage collection and shared data, where permissible;

Support for truly functional programming languages, making your programs easier to understand and debug;

A concurrency-oriented platform, allowing users to spawn, monitor, and communicate with lightweight processes, making it easy for your IoT devices to perform tasks simultaneously;

A rich set of networking APIs, for writing robust IoT applications that communicate over IP networks;

A rich set of APIs for interfacing with standard device protocols, such as GPIO, I2C, SPI, and UART;

And more!

Why Erlang/Elixir?

The environments on which AtomVM applications are deployed are significantly more constrained than typical programming environments. For example, the typical ESP32 ships with 520K of RAM and 4MB of flash storage, roughly the specs of a mind 1980s desktop computer. Moreover, most micro-controller environments do not support native POSIX APIs for interfacing with an operating system, and in many cases, common operating system abstractions, such as processes, threads, or files, are simply unavailable.

However, because the BEAM is provides a pre-emptive multitasking environment for your applications, many of the common operating system abstractions, particularly involving threading and concurrency, are simply not needed. As concurrently-oriented languages, Erlang and Elixir support lightweight “processes”, with message passing as the mechanism for inter-(erlang)process communication, pre-emptive multi-tasking, and per-process heap allocation and garbage collection.

In many ways, the programming model for Erlang and Elixir is closer to that of an operating system and multiple concurrent processes running on it, where operating system processes are single execution units, communicate through message passing (signals), and don’t share any state with one another. Contrast that with most popular programming languages today (C, C++, Java, Python, etc), which use threading abstractions to achieve concurrency within a single memory space, and which subsequently require close attention to cases in which multiple CPUs operate on a shared region of memory, requiring threads, locks, semaphores, and so forth.

As an implementation of the BEAM, AtomVM provides a modern, memory managed, and concurrency-oriented environment for developing applications on small devices. This makes writing concurrent code for micro-controllers (e.g., and application that reads sensor data, services HTTP requests, and updates the system clock, all at the same time) incredibly simple and natural – far easier than writing programs that use concurrency than C, C++, or even, for example, Micropython.

In addition, because it is targeted for micro-controller environments, AtomVM provides interfaces for integrating with features commonly seen on micro-controllers, such as GPIO pins, analog-to-digital conversion, and common industry peripheral interfaces, such as I2C, SPI, and UART, making AtomVM a rich platform for developing IoT applications.

Finally, one of the exciting aspects about modern micro-controllers, such as the ESP32, is their integration with modern networking technologies, such as WiFi and Bluetooth. AtomVM leverages Erlang and Elixir’s natural affinity with telecommunications technologies to open up further possibilities for developing networked and wireless IoT devices.

We think you will agree that AtomVM provides a compelling environment not only for Erlang and Elixir development, but also as a home for interesting and fun IoT projects.

Design Philosophy

AtomVM is designed from the start to run on small, cheap embedded devices, where system resources (memory, cpu, storage) are tightly constrained. The smallest environment in which AtomVM runs has around 512k of addressable RAM, some of which is used by the underlying runtime (FreeRTOS), and some of which is used by the AtomVM virtual machine, itself, leaving even less RAM for your own applications. Where there is a tradeoff between memory consumption and performance, minimizing memory consumption (and heap fragmentation) always wins.

From the developer’s point of view, AtomVM is designed to make use of the existing tool chain from the Erlang and Elixir ecosystems. This includes the Erlang and Elixir compilers, which will compile Erlang and Elixir source code to BEAM bytecode. Where possible, AtomVM makes use of existing tool chains to reduce the amount of unnecessary features in AtomVM, thus reducing complexity, as well as the amount of system resources in use by the runtime. AtomVM is designed to be as small and lean as possible, providing as many resources to user applications, as possible.

Licensing

AtomVM is licensed under the terms of the Apache2 and LGPLv2 licenses.

Source Code

The AtomVM Github Repository contains the AtomVM source code, including the AtomVM virtual machine and core libraries. The AtomVM Build Instructions contains instructions for building AtomVM for Generic UNIX, ESP32, and STM32 platforms.

Contributing

The AtomVM community welcomes contributions tot he AtomVM code base and upstream and downstream projects. Please see the contributing guidelines for information about how to contribute.

AtomVM developers can be reached on the #AtomVM discord server.

Where to go from here

The following guides provide more detailed information about getting started with the AtomVM virtual machine, how to develop and deploy applications, and implementation information, for anyone interested in getting more involved:

Getting Started Guide

Programmers Guide

Example Programs

Build Instructions